Wood Worsted Mill Photographs 6510/002 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Wood Worsted Mill Photographs
1905-1958
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Wood Worsted Mill
6510/002 P
0.44 cubic feet
0.4 linear ft.
Gelatin silver print, photographs.
Images depict the 1905 construction of Wood Mill in Lawrence, Massachusetts, and the demolition of that mill in 1958.
10060788
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
R. Miles, October 03, 2017
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, November 07, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The Wood Worsted Mill is located at South Union St. and Merrimack Street, on the south bank of the Merrimack River, in Lawrence, Massachusetts. The mill building was constructed between 1906 and 1909 for the American Woolen Company, and was dubbed by some locals as the "eighth wonder of the world" due to its size. It is a six story brick building that is 1,300 feet (400 m) long and 125 feet (38 m) high, and encompasses some 17 miles (27 km) of aisles. Its purpose when built was to perform the complete textile manufacturing cycle of worsted woolens, from raw material to finished fabric, under a single roof.
Scope and Contents
Nine photographs, mostly dated October 8, 1905, showing the construction of the Wood Worsted Mill, of the American Woolen Company, in Lawrence, Massachusetts. Fifteen photographs showing the 1958 demolition of the Wood Worsted Mill in Lawrence, Massachusetts.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6510: American Woolen Company Collection 6510 PUBS: American Woolen Company Publications 6510/001: American Woolen Company Records 6510/003: Andrew G. Pierce Papers 6510/004: Ayer Mill Records 6510/005: Benjamin Duce & Albert Greenwood Papers 6510/006: Bruno J. Falanga Papers 6510/007: Francis W. White Papers 6510/008: John J. Howell Papers 6510/009: Ralph L. Sheridan Papers 6510/010: William H. Baker Papers
Male employees; Lost architecture; Textile factories; Textile factories -- Design and construction; Textile workers; Wrecking; Andover (Mass.); Lawrence (Mass.); Shawsheen Station (Andover, Mass.); Shawsheen Village (Mass.); American Woolen Company; Wood Worsted Mill (Lawrence, Mass.); Wood Worsted Mills Overseers Association
10060788
- Construction Photos (Oct. 8, 1905) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 1: Construction of the Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass.: First section near the front of the building, 1905; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Image depicts large stone blocks in foreground with crane in background; workmen visible in left background; bridge over Merrimack River visible in background. Dated Oct. 8, 1905. The Wood Worsted Mill was owned by the American Woolen Company. 17 x 12 cm.
    Format: Black and White photograph.
  - Item 2: Construction of the Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass.: View of open excavation area, 1905; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts a large open area where excavation has already taken place. First section of mill to be built here. Workmen visible in background. Dated Oct. 8, 1905. The Wood Worsted Mill was owned by the American Woolen Company. 17 x 12 cm.
  - Item 3: Construction of the Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass.: Second section of building, 1905; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts a large open area where the second section of the building would be placed. Workmen visible in foreground; Merrimack River visible in background. Dated Oct. 8, 1905. The Wood Worsted Mill was owned by the American Woolen Company. 17 x 12 cm.
  - Item 4: Construction of the Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass.: Wood forms for concrete wall, 1905; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts the wood forms in the background for the concrete wall to be erected. Workman with wheelbarrow in foreground; other workmen visible in left background. Dated Oct. 8, 1905. The Wood Worsted Mill was owned by the American Woolen Company. 17 x 12 cm.
  - Item 5: Construction of the Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass.: Overview of excavated area, 1905; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts an overview of the excavated area for the mill construction. Burning brush pile in right middle ground; Merrimack River barely visible on the left. Dated Oct. 8, 1905. The Wood Worsted Mill was owned by the American Woolen Company. 17 x 12 cm.
  - Item 6: Construction of the Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass.: Part of third section of building, 1905; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts a view of the area where the third section of the building would be built; foundation has been partially dug out; wood forms for retaining wall on left. Dated Oct. 8, 1905. The Wood Worsted Mill was owned by the American Woolen Company. 17 x 12 cm.
  - Item 7: Construction of the Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass.: Location of the power house, 1905; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts the area where the power house was to be built. Laborers have begun digging for a foundation; horses and wagons are visible. Dated Oct. 8, 1905. The Wood Worsted Mill was owned by the American Woolen Company. 17 x 12 cm.
  - Item 8: Construction of the Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass.: Overview of construction area, 1905; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts an overview of the construction area. Similar to box 1, folder 1, item 5. Dated Oct. 8, 1905. The Wood Worsted Mill was owned by the American Woolen Company. 17 x 12 cm.
  - Item 9: Construction of the Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass.: Concrete wall running length of area, 1905; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Image depicts a view of the concrete wall erected; it runs to within 40 feet of the little white house in the background; total length 1485 feet. The Wood Worsted Mill was owned by the American Woolen Company. 17.75 x 12.5 cm.
- Demolition Photos, 1954-1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 1: Shawsheen Station, Boston & Maine Railroad, Andover, Mass, 1954; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    ca1954. Image depicts the Shawsheen Village train station, with the former American Woolen Company building in the background. 25.5 x 21 cm.
  - Item 2: Demolition of the north wing of the Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass, 1958; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Image depicts the demolition of the north wing of the Wood Worsted Mill in Lawrence, Mass.; crane with wrecking ball works on north side; clock over entrance still visible on right. The Wood Mill was owned by the American Woolen Company. 20.5 x 25.5 cm.
  - Item 3: Demolition of the north wing of the Wood Mill inside the courtyard, Lawrence, Mass, 1958; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Image depicts the demolition of the north wing of the Wood Worsted Mill in Lawrence, Mass. as seen from within the courtyard; demolition debris along the ground; fourth floor has been leveled. The Wood Mill was owned by the American Woolen Company. 25.5 x 20.5 cm.
  - Item 4: Demolition near entrance of the Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass., 1958; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Image depicts the demolition near the entrance of the Wood Worsted Mill on the north wing. Holes evident in building facade; workman visible at the top of the crane. The Wood Mill was owned by the American Woolen Company. 20.5 x 25.5 cm.
  - Item 5: Overview of demolition of the north wing of the Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass, 1958; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Image depicts the demolition of the north wing of the Wood Worsted Mill in Lawrence, Mass., showing the complete destruction of the face of the building including the entrance. The Merrimack River is visible to the left. The Wood Mill was owned by the American Woolen Company. See folder 1, item 14 for an almost identical view. 25.5 x 20.5 cm.
  - Item 6: Close-up view of clock at entrance of the north wing of the Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass., before demolition, 1958; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Image depicts the clock over the entrance of the north wing of the Wood Worsted Mill in Lawrence, Mass., before the wrecking crane has reached it. Some demolition already visible to the left. The Wood Mill was owned by the American Woolen Company. See also folder 1, item 7-9. 25.5 x 20.5 cm.
  - Item 7: Another view of clock at entrance of the north wing of the Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass., before demolition, 1958; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Image depicts the clock over the entrance of the north wing of the Wood Worsted Mill in Lawrence, Mass., before demolition has begun. The Wood Mill was owned by the American Woolen Company. See also folder 1, item 6 and folder 1, item 8-9. 25.5 x 20.5 cm.
  - Item 8: Another view of clock at entrance of the north wing of the Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass., before demolition, 1958; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Image depicts the clock over the entrance of the north wing of the Wood Worsted Mill in Lawrence, Mass., before demolition has begun. Workmen are visible at the top of the crane in the upper left corner of the photo. The Wood Mill was owned by the American Woolen Company. See also folder 1, item 6-7 and folder 1, item 9. 20.5 x 25.5 cm.
  - Item 9: Another view of clock at entrance of the north wing of the Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass., 1958; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Image depicts the clock over the entrance of the north wing of the Wood Worsted Mill in Lawrence, Mass. Demolition of the area beyond it clearly visible. Workmen visible at tope of construction crane (seen at left). The Wood Mill was owned by the American Woolen Company. See also folder 1, item 6-8. 20.5 x 25.5 cm.
  - Item 10: Bystanders watch the demolition of the north wing of the Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass, 1958; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Image depicts bystanders standing on a bridge over the Merrimack River, observing the demolition of the north wing of the Wood Worsted Mill in Lawrence, Mass. From this angle, demolition appears almost complete. The Wood Mill was owned by the American Woolen Company. 25.5 x 20.5 cm.
  - Item 11: Demolition of the north wing of the Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass., 1958; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Image depicts the demolition of the north wing of the Wood Worsted Mill in Lawrence, Mass., from an angle along the river (probably from a bridge). Large cloud of dust from the wreckage is visible. See folder 1, item 12 for an almost identical view. The Wood Mill was owned by the American Woolen Company. 25.25 x 20.5 cm.
  - Item 12: Demolition of the north wing of the Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass., from the Merrimack River, 1958; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Image depicts the demolition of the north wing of the Wood Worsted Mill in Lawrence, Mass., from an angle along the river (probably from a bridge). Large cloud of dust from the wreckage is visible. See folder 1, item 11 for an almost identical view. The Wood Mill was owned by the American Woolen Company. 25.25 x 20.5 cm.
  - Item 13: Close-up view of the debris from the demolition of the north wing of the Wood Mill, Lawrence, Mass, 1958; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Image depicts the debris from the demolition of the north wing of the Wood Worsted Mill in Lawrence, Mass.; open interior walls are visible in the background. The Wood Mill was owned by the American Woolen Company. 20.5 x 25.5 cm.
  - Item 14: Overview of the demolition of the north wing of the Wood Mills, Lawrence, Mass., 1958; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Image depicts the demolition of the north wing of the Wood Worsted Mill in Lawrence, Mass., showing the complete destruction of the face of the building including the entrance. More demolition is evident in the left background. The Merrimack River is visible to the left. The Wood Mill was owned by the American Woolen Company. See folder 1, item 5 for an almost identical view. 25.5 x 20.5 cm.
  - Item 15: Demolition of the north wing of the Wood Mills, Lawrence, Mass., 1958; Black and White photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Image depicts the demolition of the north wing of the Wood Worsted Mill in Lawrence, Mass., showing the gutted interior and partially remaining outside walls. The Wood Mill was owned by the American Woolen Company. 25.5 x 20.5 cm.
- Wood Worsted Mills - Overseers Association. Wardhurst, Sept. 23, 1922, Black and White photograph (Box 2, Folder 1)
  panoramic group photo